If you walked into a cafe or pub in the UK a few years ago, chances were you’d enter a room filled with cigarette smoke.
要是在几年前走进英国的一家咖啡馆或酒吧，你大概率会踏入一间烟雾缭绕的屋子。
The aroma of burning tobacco lingered on your clothes for the rest of day and your health took a battering from passive smoking.
燃烧烟草的气味会在你衣服上残留一整天，你的健康也会因吸二手烟而受损。
It’s no wonder that in many countries smoking in public places has now been banned, and those who choose to do it have to inhale on the pavements outside.
难怪如今许多国家都已禁止在公共场所吸烟，那些仍想抽烟的人只能去外面的人行道上过把瘾。
Laws restricting where people can light up and repeated health warnings have seen many people quit the habit.
限制吸烟场所的法规以及反复的健康警示，让很多人戒掉了吸烟的习惯。
But despite a decline in smoking rates worldwide, a report published in the medical journal The Lancet in 2017 found that smoking causes one in ten deaths worldwide, half of them in just four countries - China, India, the US and Russia.
但尽管全球吸烟率有所下降，2017年发表在医学期刊《柳叶刀》上的一份报告却指出，全球十分之一的死亡案例由吸烟导致，其中半数集中在四个国家——中国、印度、美国和俄罗斯。
When population growth is taken into account, there is actually an increase in the overall number of smokers.
如果把人口增长因素考虑在内，吸烟者的总人数其实是在上升的。
So why - despite the warning signs - are these people still doing it?
那么，为什么明明有诸多警示，这些人还是不愿戒烟呢？
Much of it seems to be connected to people’s cultural, economic and social background.
这在很大程度上似乎与人们的文化、经济和社会背景有关。
In the UK, for example, the Office for National Statistics found that people living on a low income are disproportionately likely to smoke.
例如，英国国家统计局发现，低收入人群的吸烟比例极高。
And one in four manual workers smokes, compared with one in ten of those in professional or managerial jobs.
体力劳动者中四分之一的人有吸烟习惯，而专业人士或管理人员的吸烟比例仅为十分之一。
Dr Leonie Brose from King's College London, writing about this for the BBC, says there are “startling” regional variations with many more pregnant women smoking in deprived areas.
伦敦国王学院的莉奥妮·布罗斯博士在为英国广播公司撰写相关文章时表示，吸烟情况存在“令人震惊的”地区差异，贫困地区吸烟的孕妇数量要多得多。
And people with mental health problems are “50% more likely to smoke than the rest of the population”.
此外，有心理健康问题的人群“吸烟的可能性比普通人群高出50%”。
She suggests these groups can have higher levels of dependence, making it harder to give up and are also more likely to be around other smokers, making it seem like normal behaviour.
她指出，这些群体对香烟的依赖程度更高，因此更难戒烟，而且他们身边吸烟的人也更多，这让吸烟看起来成了一种正常行为。
Increasing the price of cigarettes and making packaging plainer are two ways to discourage smoking; and lower-risk nicotine patches and e-cigarettes are available as an alternative, though they can be just as addictive.
提高香烟价格、简化香烟包装是两种抑制吸烟的手段；同时市面上也有低风险的尼古丁贴片和电子烟作为替代品，不过这些产品同样可能让人上瘾。
It’s obvious something needs to be done and recently the UK government pledged to end smoking in England by 2030 as part of a range of measures to tackle the causes of preventable ill health.
显然，我们必须采取行动了。近日，英国政府承诺，作为一系列应对可预防性健康问题诱因的措施之一，将在2030年前彻底终结英格兰地区的吸烟现象。
But as Dr Leonie Brose writes, “with more than 200 deaths in England per day [caused by smoking-related diseases,] that’s the equivalent to a plane crashing every day.”
但正如莉奥妮·布罗斯博士所写：“英格兰每天有超过200人死于吸烟相关疾病，这相当于每天都有一架飞机坠毁。”
Imagine what the number must be globally.
试想一下，全球的死亡数字该有多么触目惊心。